step in this learning formula is practice. The well-known Sanskrit saying
karat karat abhyas ke, jad mati hot sujan translates to practice makes perfect
emphasizing that repeated practice leads to mastery. The best way to practice is
by solving past year papers and take mock tests. These tools helps you
identify mistakes you might make on the exam day. It is better to make the learn
from mistakes in a mock test than to make them during the actual exam.
Practicing this way helps you spot silly mistakes and understand how to manage
your time efficiently under exam conditions.
Moving ahead, just like pre-votes exam prepare you for final exam by
highlighting errors to avoid. Regular practice is essential for mastering what
you have learned. Do not just take mock test, analyze your mistakes
and note them down in a separate notebook. This way you can review and
avoid these mistakes before exams. Now quiz station, every chapter includes
quiz stations with practice questions. These help you test to
understand the concepts right after you study a topic.
Now I will read the acknowledgment.
I begin by bowing down to the mighty Lord Ganesh, the revered
Vighna Harta. His divine grace has endured the smooth complexion of this
book, clearing all obstacles from my path. I bow down to Mahasaraswati, to my
ancestors and special thanks to my family. The creation of this book is the
result of many people standing by my side, helping, motivating and guiding me.
Their unwavering support and encouragement have been instrumental in
bringing this work to life. I am deeply grateful to Shri Sardar Girdhar
ji, late Shri Ram ji. One of the most rewarding career
opportunities after clearing the UGC net exam is becoming an assistant
professor in colleges and universities. The table below highlights the pay scale
structure for various academic positions, showcasing the financial benefits of
pursuing this career path. In the academic pay scale, the table given on the left
side, the level indicates the hierarchical position of a faculty member in college
and universities. This level is determined based on a combination of
factors including years of experience, academic qualification and the number of
research papers published. When an individual clears UGC net, they become
eligible for the position of assistant professor, starting typically at the
level 10. With consistent performance, research, contribution and experience,
they can progress to higher levels. In the addition of basic salary given in
the table above, academic professionals are entitled to HRA that is house rent
allowance, TA that is travel allowance and GP that is grade pay which enhance
their overall compensation. This financial stability combined with the
prestige of teaching makes academia a higher attractive
career option post UGC net.
Eligibility in the case of special degree certificate programs. If you have
a postgraduate diploma or certificate from an Indian or foreign university, you
need to check if it's equivalent to the master's degree from a recognized
university. For this, contact the Association of Indian Universities, AIU
in New Delhi. Law students should check with the Bar Council of India. Candidates
with a four-year or eight-year semester batch bachelor degrees need at least
75 marks, 75% marks or equivalent grade. There is a 5% relaxation for the Dalits.
Net eligibility. If you qualify for the net with a four-year bachelor's degree,
you are eligible for the junior research fellowship that is JRF and PhD admission
but not for appointment as an assistant professor. Final year students
for a four-year bachelor degree.
Candidates should select their UGC net paper to subject based on their postgraduate
specialization. For example, a student with an MA in political science should
choose political science as their paper to subject. If a candidate's postgraduate
degree is in subject not listed by the UGC, they may choose a closely related
subject from the available option.
Study timetable for covering UGC net paper 1 syllabus in just 33 days.
In this book, the 10 units of the UGC net paper 1 syllabus have been meticulously
divided into 33 chapters. This structured approach allows you to focus on
completing one chapter per day enabling you to finish the entire syllabus in
just 33 days. The reason behind this approach is to prevent students from
feeling overwhelmed by a single large unit. By breaking down the syllabus into
smaller manageable chapters, we help you cover the material gradually and
systematically reducing stress and making the study process more manageable.
This method ensures a study progression through the syllabus which maintaining a sense of
accomplishment as you complete each chapter.
Creating a unit-wise timetable and alternative method involves creating a well-structured
unit-wise timetable. This approach is beneficial for those who prefer a balanced
study schedule that accommodates both challenging and easier topics. Here is a
simple timetable that you may find relatable and help you cover the syllabus
efficiently.
To prevent fatigue and maintain motivation, alternate between challenging and easier units.
For instance, pair units like teaching aptitude generally easier with research aptitude that is more
challenging. The method helps you keep study session balanced and less
overwhelming. Units that require heavy memorization such as ICT, people and
environment and higher education can be mentally exhausting. Mix this with
practical portions like data interpretation and mathematical reasoning
to give your brain a break and enhance retention. This strategy helps manage
cognitive load and improves overall learning efficiency. Allocate extra time
each day to practice questions from practical units such as mathematical
reasoning and data interpretation. Adding 30 minutes of practice will help you build
proficiency and improve problem solving. Since every student has unique strength
and weakness, you might find certain topics easier or more challenging than
others. Use the tips shared above to design a timetable that suits your
specific need. Adjust the sample timetable based on your comfort level
with different units and progress to create a study plan that works best for
you. After designing a full syllabus timetable, it is equally
important to design a study schedule. Study schedule will help you meet your
targets regularly and achieve the overall goals of finishing the syllabus.
To complete the next paper 1 syllabus in approximately 30 days, it is advisable
to devote at least 4 hours daily to preparation. Here is a recommendation
breakdown of your daily study time. If traditional timetable haven't worked for
you, here is an alternate approach. To plan your net preparation, instead of
focusing on unit wise study plan, adopt a topic wise approach using this three
step formula. The foundation of an efficient timetable is understanding how
many days you have before the exam. For example, if you have 100 days left, this
clarity will help in distributing topics evenly and avoiding last minute
cramming. Instead of seeing the syllabus as large, overwhelming units, break it
down into simpler, smaller and specific topics. Count how many topics you need to
cover from all the 10 units. For example, instead of just thinking about R.A.
that is research aptitude, as a whole list out quality qualitative research,
sampling and hypothesis testing, this book also uses the same approach by
dividing each unit into individual topics. You can easily find a comprehensive
list of all the topics in the timetable, which shows what all the topics that you
need to study under each unit. Percentage, the type of question I will get in the
paper 1, I am discussing that right now. Percentage, 50% question that you see in
exam falls into this category of easy questioning, means 50% of the
students can easily, 50% of students nain, the paper like have 100 questions, then 50 of them are easy.
Strategies to solve, do not feel obligated to solve the exam paper in the order the
question are presented. Instead start by answering all the easy questions first.
This will give you a stance of accomplishment and boost your confidence
when you will feel that you have solved many questions correctly. Additionally,
it is important not to note that when we solve easy questions towards the end,
we often make errors due to time pressure. We might misread or misinterpret the question
or harshly choose an option. Therefore, it is advisable to tackle easy questions
from first when you have ample time to read and answer the question carefully.
30 of them, 30% of them are false, falls into the category of difficult level questioning.
This, these question requires more efforts and critical thinking. You may need to apply
your knowledge, analysis and concept and sometimes make educated guesses to arrive
at the correct answer. To solve these kind of questions, apply the principle of elimination
by first identifying and discarding the option that you know are definitely incorrect.
This method simplifies complex questions and improve your chances of selecting right answers.
20% of the exams falls under the category of challenging questions. These questions
require more efforts and critical thinking. You may need to apply more knowledge,
analyze the concept and sometimes make educated guesses to arrive at the correct answers.
Feeling anxiety or anxious before an exam is completely normal, you are not alone in this
feeling with this way. Every UGC net and students across the country is dealing with similar feeling
stress. Remember the mountain you add that says, meaning fear is something everyone experiences.
Even the most accomplished individual. But what you do when anxiety strikes in the middle of the
exam, here's the quick mantra to regain focus and calm your nerves. Deep breathing, stay hydrated,
do not panic, do not panic if you forget. Do not calculate your marks during the exam.
Read question twice, answer all questions, use bilingual reading. Prioritize accuracy over speed,
avoid mental calculation to prevent errors, avoid doing calculation in your head. Use rough paper
for data interpretation and mathematical reasoning questions. Now the syllabus is,
unit 1 is teaching aptitude, unit 2 research aptitude, unit 3 comprehension followed by
communication, mathematical reasoning and aptitude, logical reasoning, data interpretation,
information communication technology that is ICT, people development and environment and last,
higher education system. The official net syllabus serves as a broad guideline that
does not include every topic that may appear in the exam. While it outlines key subject
areas under the 10 unit, the actual question often cover additional concept and topic not
explicitly mentioned in the syllabus. To bridge this gap, we have conducted a comprehensive
analysis of previous year's questions that is from 2014 to 2025. Based on this analysis,
we have compiled an extensive list of topics that are asked in previous papers. Now,
I should shut myself off because I am continuously speaking for 15 minutes right now. This may help
you. Okay. Garima Singh, over and out.